<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prolocutour, or, a preparative for peace.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91065</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864836</idno>
  <idno type="VID">162369</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240911815</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3657</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E469_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205463</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864836</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864836e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162369)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E469[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prolocutour, or, a preparative for peace.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Yeer, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162369:1"/>
            <p>THE PROLOCVTOVR, <hi>OR,</hi> A Preparative for PEACE.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeer. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:162369:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:162369:2"/>
            <head>THE PROLOCVTOVR, <hi>OR,</hi> A Preparative for Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hall the <hi>Sword</hi> devour for ever? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.26. no; Oh thou Sword of the Lord, how long will it be ere thou ceaze? turn againe into thy scabbard, rest, and be still. <hi>Ier.</hi> 47.6. For many which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver saw a man wounded, much lesse slaine, now in the midst of wounds, and death, how can they but stand appalled? To behold a particular man kill himself, would daunt a tender heart; who can then but faint to see a whol Nation draw upon it self? <hi>Whence are Warres and Contentions? are they not hence, even from the lusts that fight in your Members?</hi> 4 <hi>Iames.</hi> 1. Are there not some distempered affections amongst us? is there not a popular phrenzy? Yes, <hi>Quis furor oh cives?</hi> The Kingdome is like to give herself the deadly stabbe, and to prove <hi>felo de se.</hi> It is an act of charity then, and naturall compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, to hold your hands, nay to endeavour to take the weapons out of your hands, for <hi>quae tanta licentia ferri?</hi> But how shall we compose this difference, pacify this rage? Nature (me thinks) might doe much to appease this quarrell, policy more, religion most of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nature,</hi> for Nature which is a conserver of her self, and hath taken upon her to be the Squire of the body to defend a being, will that suffer you to commit such outrages? No, if ye would consult with Nature, that would shame you, confound you in this truculent Designe. Nature likes not to have any such mortall prizes playd upon her stage, Nature loves not the cut-throat:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:162369:3"/> Hath she then bred you, and fed you, skinned you smooth, and nou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed you gentle, seated courtesy in your browes, and huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in your hearts, put you to school where you might learne so many principles of nature, and grounds of meekness, and mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, now to prove so savage? There is a poor relique in such of Nature, yea little left of the man; No, the same creature is gone, and a wilde beast is stept up in the stead, man is become a Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard or Tyger, for whilst ye are thus implacable, are ye not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall? But the plea of Nature is yet stronger against you, when she hath bound you to Amity, and Vnity with firmer links, even of the same Country, and the same acquaintance, and the same kindred. All of you being of the same Country, most of you of the same acquaintance, many of you of the same kindred. And shall the thoughts of Country, acquaintance, kindred, now be laid aside, that ye may have the freet liberty to worke mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all mischiefs? No, Country should prevaile with you for a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triman is precious in <hi>Turkey,</hi> in the <hi>Indies;</hi> they which have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled all parts, find that they will leave all to embrace a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man, to endeere themselves to a Country-man. And shall a Country-man be acceptable abroad, contemptible at home? have we forgotten the common soyle we tread upon, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ayre we breath in? what pollute this soyle with our owne blood, corrupt this ayre with the dying gaspes of Natives? shall we foster a Countrey-man else-where, and braine him here? no, the name of Country should put more tender affections into us, into you. And for acquaintance, how doth it knit and combine? friends seem to incorporate, yea to inanimate one another, as if they had but the same flesh in severall pieces, yea the same soul to quicken many Individualls; for friends, what are they but so many multiplyed selves? deere and entire is the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of friendship, for a friend that is unto thee as thine own soul. 13 <hi>Deutr.</hi> 6. Friendship is <hi>ferrumen animarum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naz.</note> the folder of spirits, the cement of familiarity; acquaintance is the loadstone of the feet to draw them together, and the chiming of tongues to make one hammar, (as it were) to strike after another, for friends are never well till they be pacing, and parlying together; their brests are open, for no secrets amongst friends; their hearts spring, or faint at the presence or absence of one another,<note place="margin">Bern.</note> for <hi>sine quo vivere mori,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom to live is to dye. A man will search the world
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162369:3"/> through for a friend, a friend is the gemme of price in this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cabinet. And shall not the thought of friends keep the age peaceable? what hold thy poll-axe over that head that hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised so much good to thee! bend thy speare against that brest where liveth an heart that hath wished thee all true happiness! shall thy plundering horse neigh at that threshold, or thy keene sword glitter under that roof, where all manner of ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dness hath been exprest! what, rifle the coffers, or cut the heart-strings of thy deerest friends? Oh that all courteous passages, and sweet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchanges of favour can be so soon forgotten! Nature here hath a strong accusation against thee for the neglect of acquaintance, that the friend should be made such a stranger. And what shall we say to kindred? The remembrance of kindred? The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of kindred is a kind of enchantment unto Peace, <hi>for let there be no strife between thee and me, for we are brethren,</hi> 13 <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. If the consideration of pedigrees, that the same nest hath hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, or the same stock hath branched them forth will not keep men quiet, what can? Nature can do no more then carry you home to the same cradle that rocked you, or to the same brests that nourced you. Have your fathers sent you out of the same loynes, and your Mothers brought you forth out of the same wombe, to cleave and quarter one another, to prove such a <hi>Cadmus</hi> race? Oh if many of you could leave the forced titles of Voluntieres, Troopers, &amp;c. and call your selves your Fathers children, to thinke that ye are derived from the same family, that that good old man that now lies mouldering under a grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, and consuming into gelly, left you all his owne name, that he gave you many a kisse in his life-time, that ye might be the loving children of the same Father; yea and gave you a dying charge, that for all the cost he had bestowed upon you, the care he had taken for you, the teares he had shed for you, the Armes and jewells he left you, that ye would for the honor of his blood, and out of reverence to his dying requests live in peace together, doubtless this would take downe your haughty resolutions, and quench your fiery expressions. For oh that ye should undermine the foundations of your owne families, pull downe the crefts of your owne Scutcheons, that where there hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the infusion of the same blood, there should be now the effusion of the same blood; that kindred should be sundered; that Pedigree should
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162369:4"/> hew downe her owne fayre spreading tree, and not to leave her issue a branch to spring out of the old stock, that consanguinity should be turned into exanguinity! Oh ponder upon these things, and see how Nature intercedes for Peace, she beseecheth you by all those deere Remembrancers of hers ye carry about you, that ye would not renew these fatall strokes, for so long as ye continue these Warres, ye warre against Nature; Nature suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in these things, and by these things ye will scarce at last leave any mention of Nature amongst you. She desireth you once more to heare her Solicitors; Ye are all Country-men, and shall Country-men be so fell and furious against one another? or shall the Country fall by the hands of her owne Champions, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors? Ye are most of the same acquaintance, and shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance wax unkest and unkent? shall <hi>juratissimi amici</hi> prove <hi>juratissimi inimici?</hi> sworn friends turn vaved enemies? And to conclude, ye are many of you of the same kindred, and will ye march to the confusion of one another, through the bowells of your owne linage, through a deluge of blood gushing out of the warme springs of your own kindred? No, Country, acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, kindred, forbid these things; Oh then that so long as ye feel Nature stirring in you, that ye can give the check to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsions of Nature! No, the Warres must ceaze, Nature hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged them unlawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly Policy.</hi> For how can Policy approve of these Warres? no, true Policy is Secretary of State to that great Empresse of the whole world, called Politcy. Policy then will never like of those things that she seeth work to the destruction of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales. Policy holds her self to her grounds, and these Warres, and her grounds are incompatible.</p>
            <p>For first, a ground of Policy it is to maintaine Order. Let Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be destroyed, and the nerve of Policy is weakened, yea the Arch of it shattered, and demolished. What doth Policy more ayme at, then to keep men within their just measures, to reteine every one in their due degrees. If the Head once lose the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and command, all the members turne Male-contents, and are but like a company of unruly Generalls; Government is then confusion, and Order Faction; like the temper of Nature, let loose to the distemper of every severall humour, or a ship well guided, after the Master is over-mastered, left to the steering of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162369:4"/> every unexperienced Boat-swaine. Take away Order, and take away the security of the Common-wealth, for this is the hinge of community, the publique Buttresse. If the Principall may not be obeyed, what Superiority will there be submitted to? no it is to extirpate, exregnate all authority, even for servants to rise up against their Masters, for children to pluck their Parents by the throat, for the Wife to destroy her Husband that lay by her sides, for the Peasant to kill the yeoman, the yeoman to murder the Gentleman, the Gentleman to shed the blood of the Knight, the Knight to stabbe the Nobleman, Societies to slaughter their su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Intendents. Incorporations to butcher their Magistrates, and in fine for the Commons to massacre Parliaments. For that which is denied to the Highest, will never be granted to men of inferior degree; no this spark is ready to set al in combustion, even to kindle a generall flame; for when Order is taken away, Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy succeeds, and what can we look for out of Anarchy, but for a clew of mischiefs? Oh therefore what are ye doing? even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing the goodliest frame of Government under heaven; for whereas superiors formerly lived no where with more obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance, now no where they shall live with more disdaigne; for the Hinde will scorne to be subject to the chief man in the Parish, and every despicable person with a sword by his side, and a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll in his hand, will brave upon men worth hundreds, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands. It is not the painted portall, nor the fitted gowne that will any longer beget awe; No, where the Prince is not reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, a generall disobedience runs through the whole Nation. If this were Policy therefore, Policy should have forgotten one of her chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f State-Maximes, for how can she preserve States with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Order? no, It is Gods mercy (even for want of this) that we are not all before this time, through some popular rage, buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a common grave. Policy then even for this disclaimeth the Warre.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is a ground of Policy to worke her ends by fayre meanes. If she hath the best things in the world to undertake, she likes no acerbity in the carriage; no, Policy is the true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor of the Common-Wealth, the great Statist, therefore she contrives all her publique well-fare by well-fare, that is, by pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid and gentle passages. If there be any harmfull accidents here, the crafty Agent is suspected, not the true Politician, because
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162369:5"/> true policy never doth any grievous, damnifying things; No, <hi>Be wise as Serpents, but innocent as Doves.</hi> 10. <hi>Matt.</hi> 16. To bring in an Innovation then by violence, what is this but to contest with Policy? especially such a violence as makes the Nobles to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plume the Commons, and the Commons to eviscerate the Nobles, for men in gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll to fire Cities, and forrage fields, to make ships ly at anchor in the haven, and the wares to moath-cat in the shoppe, to melt all the plate of the Land into a Campe-fee, and that which the Providence of many Ages hath gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to consume in a few yeers. Policy liketh not of Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with such weakening and wasting of Common-weales. Innovations she ever counts dangerous, but when they come to be compelled, mischievous; for if a Fabrick be out of frame, it must be new-settled with tenderness, or else a man may have the house on his head instead of repayring it; if the body be valetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, the Malignancy must be fetched away by degrees, lest in stead of purging out the evill humours, thou drawest out the vitall spirits. <hi>I will drive softly,</hi> (said <hi>Iacob) according to the pace of the cattell.</hi> 33 <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. lest in getting the drove home too fast, he might leave part of it dead by the way. <hi>He that wringeth the nose, forceth out blood.</hi> 30 <hi>Prov.</hi> 33. Fetch out the filth, but doe not force out blood; better leave some filth till another time, then to streine so hard, till thou openest the Orifices. Changes then must be wrought by the sweetness of Counsell, and the equity of things presented to the Vnderstanding, for if our judgement cannot apprehend the conveniency of a request, our great hearts will never yeeld to compulsion. The sword can never satisfy us, for the very shaking of that makes us rather obstinate, then tractable. If we be to doe all as our Prudence shall direct us, will we ever be taught Wisedome by the Battle-axe? No, the State allows no such engine of Policy for Princes. Policy, if she in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any Innovation, she will either incline it, or decline it; if she cannot <hi>viam invenire,</hi> she will not <hi>facere;</hi> no, she works all by faire means.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is a ground of Policy to Remunerate; for that is not Policy that waxes unkind upon courtesies received, or bicker so soon as she is pleasured: No, t is were rather to be Tetricall than Politique; for what discreet person will quarrell upon a good turne received? Such a one should be like a Guest, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162369:5"/> challenges his Feast-maker, when he hath fed him with all his costly dainties. But the part of Policy is to cherish good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and to honour Worth, even to stoop and cringe to Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence; yea the highest stretch of her devices, and the achme of her inventions, is to procure a remainder of Favours, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilling her good opinion of those she hath received; for the Bark will come no more at that Port where it hath been arrested for bringing in commodities. <hi>Cessat gratiarum cursus ubi recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus non fuerit,</hi> Favours cease where Thankfulnesse failes. Oh then! when a Prince hath honoured a Nation with more acts of Grace then any of his Predecessors, eased many Grievances, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with most of his Rights, complyed with his people in such high Demands; Is this a time to denounce Warre against Him? No, a man would think some Monument should be set up to His honour, or Pyramid of Gratitude erected, to immortalize His Name: These a man would expect, rather than a new Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of Iron-Bullets; this may seem State-greatnesse, but is is no Policy, because Policy loves to Remunerate.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is a ground of Policy to live answerably to her own praescript Rules; for Policy is a heedy observer of her own Principles, and carryes a sacred reverence to her own Lawes, or else she should seem to put a mock upon the world, in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the justnesse of them, or commanding obedience towards them: for it is the height of Iniquity to prescribe that to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which we will not practise our selves. Oh then, when a Kingdome is secured by a Petition of Right, so that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing should be taken of the Subject but by his own consent, to involve a State into such a War as cannot be maintained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forcing the estate, and constreine the consents, as if men would compell both Goods and Conscience to serve their ends (whereby the Nation that is ready to be called the Kingdome of Priviledges, is now ready to be called the Kingdome of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles) how inconsiderate should this be? for what worse than to bring in a War to batter down a peoples Immunities, or to vanquish their Liberties, whereby many free Subjects are so fast locked-up in Prison, that neither Magna Charta, nor the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Right can get a Iayle-delivery for them? Oh what is now the benefit of Lawes? How are we freed from Arbitrary Government, even when the high-Court of Iustice is open?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162369:6"/> Doubtlesse all the old Patriots stand agast, and the wisest Iudges are confounded, how to settle the Subject upon his ancient Basis, the Law. If a Prince hereafter mind to Tyrannize, here is little restraint for him; he may easily enter upon our common Rights, for the gap is broken for him; he may send Pursivants, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants at Armes, imprison, plunder, take the twentith part, set an Excise upon our meat, yea beget a breed of Taxes every New-Moon, and all this by a Parliament-license: Vnhappy Warre therefore, that would still ensl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve all our Freedomes, and lay all our Lawes and Liberties a bleeding. Valour may like this War, and sunk faced Indigency, that knows not how to support her selfe but under the miseries of a decayed State, may magnify it, but true Policy will never approve of it, for this makes her live contrary to her prescript Rules.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, it is a ground of Policy to preserve her owne Forces against a common Enemy, for as nature doth not enfeeble (as nigh as she can) her own strength, but keep that entire to resist the Enemies of Nature, so Policy doth not wreck upon her Worthies, and wast her Combatants in Civill Dissentions, but layes up these as the State-store to oppugne the publique Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary. But by entring the Lists with a King, to leavy Armies, and send out numerous Hosts <hi>Cogere in ordinem</hi> to bring him to his knees; What is this but to unpeople a Country, and disarme a Kingdom against a National danger? For who may not defy us at our own doors, and put the yoak upon our necks, when we have scarce left men enough to fill our Garrisons, and meanes enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o tigge out a Navy? Any daring Invader may then have his advantage: Oh, is this to make a Nation formidable? No, to rob a Nation of her courage, and prowesse, and leave nothing but cowardize to lift up her trembling undisciplined hands to repell an enemy. If we must needs have Wars, we might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our strength in doing honourable things to the Nation, and in filleting the browes of the State with a Wreath of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Victories.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Heu quantum terrae potuit, pelagique parari</l>
               <l>Hoc quem civiles hauserunt sanguine dextra!</l>
            </q>
            <p>If our Zeale bee so hot, and Conscience calleth us up to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162369:6"/> Warres, we might go and pluck the Pope out of his Porphiry Chaire, or the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> out of his <hi>Saragli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or Mount <hi>Peli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> upon <hi>Ossa:</hi> Here are a company of such invincible <hi>Termagants</hi> lately arisen, that they feare neither <hi>Centaures</hi> nor <hi>Minotaures:</hi> Well, if their valour be so great, they might better make prooff of it any where, then in gashing the sides of their own Nation. For thus to lay all our magnanimous spirits gasping at home, whereby we are disabled to exercise puissance abroad, either to defend, or encrease the honour of the Nation; What is this but to pervert Valour, or (if we have wisdome to conceive it, and patience to heare it) insensibly to betray a State? Whatsoever stomack there may bee in it, there is little Policy; for Policy quiets all her home-bred Differences without a noise, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves her own Forces against a common Enemy.</p>
            <p>So that Policy was never called into this Councell of Warre, no, if she must fight, she likes not to fight at this weapon, called Selfe-bleed. She is put by all her ingenious Plots, and rare Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, when she is drawn into approve of this War; if you would have the Cause countenanced therefore you must get some other Patron then Policy, for with all her Mercuriall wit she cannot find out one justifying reason for it; this Cause then as it is none of the kindest, for Nature dislikes it, so it is none of the wisest, for Policy disallows it; as it wants something of the breast for Affection, so it wants something of the braine for Iudgement; guilty of much State-frowardnesse, and as much State-folly; all Policies grounds here faile her, for this course is neither tender of order, nor faire in managing, nor sensible of favours, nor carefull to preserve her owne rules, or her owne Forces; whatsoever fancied Epithet therefore can be put upon the Designe, yet it cannot be called Politique; No, the Warres must cease, if Policy may give sentence.</p>
            <p>But you will say the maine satisfaction is still behind; for though Nature and Policy have condemned the Enterprise, yet if Scripture will authorise it it shall be held lawfull. <hi>But if thou hast run with the Footmen and they have wearied thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12 <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.</note>
               <hi>how then shalt thou run with the Horsmen?</hi> If Nature and Policy out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strip this fond apprehension, then how shall it keep pace with Scripture? Shall Scripture savour that course that Nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and Policy disclaimes? No, it were a marvaile, if men
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162369:7"/> could bring God into the combination, and make him head of the Faction. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tor or Abettor, Party or Patron to such a Flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious designement. But Scripture, which is the reflexe of Gods Wisdome, the character of his Will, the scale of his Iustice, and the shining drop of his Goodnesse, doth neither afford Precept nor President to such a horrid practise. Not Precept; for <hi>My Son feare God and the King.</hi> Prov. 24 21. <hi>And I advertise thee to take heed to the mouth of the King.</hi> 8 Ecclesi. 2. <hi>Let every soule be subject to the higher Powers.</hi> Rom. 13.1. Not President; for neither Prophets, Apostles, nor Martyrs, ever gave Example of bearing Arms against their King, no not in the dayes of <hi>Ammon, Manasses, Tiberius, Nero, Dioclesian, Julian, Constantius, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stans, Valens,</hi> or any other Princes, tainted either with Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme or Heresie. And it is very improbable that that Scripture which reproves Rebellion in Heaven, that it should approve of it upon earth; that which reprehended the act of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and his traine, for being so taken with their Greatnesse, as that they would not endure a Superior, but for'd up in competition for a parity, yea sought for a Coordination; <hi>For I will ascend, and bee like the most High.</hi> 14. <hi>Isa.</hi> 14. That it should countenance the very semblance of the same act amongst men; No, <hi>if Lucifer for this was made Noctifer, then Scripture will never make such radiant stars sons of the mornning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is not credible that Scripture, which execrates Rebellion in nature (which is generally so stiled,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> and stigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised, because it is a bosome War, a heart-tumult, a mutiny of the affections) that it should tollerate a rebellion in manners, this open Rebellion that comes along with sound of Trumpet, and Banners displayed; if that bee Rebellion because it wants a rectitude, and is an incongruity (which notwithstanding is so privy, that the Eagles eye cannot oftentimes discerne it, not the searching Angell, nor observant Actor, but he that hath eyes ten thousand times brighter than the Sun, must be the close spy) then doubtlesse this practise that so faces God, and dares Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, must needs be Rebellion; for from what doth the one bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the name but from the other?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it were strange that Scripture which dislikes discord (for it cannot scarce endure that a man should have a frown in his brow, or a fret in his brest against his brother) that it should allow Sedition.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:162369:7"/>
            <p>Fourthly, that Scripture, which forbids private Murther (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for one man to kill another) that it should suffer an whole Nation to appeare in battle array against their King, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their murthering shot at him: No, it is enough to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out the sence of Scripture concerning this point, that it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals this sin with that heinous trespasse that hath sold away all right in God, and covenanted with the Divell, <hi>Witchcraft</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. and that every where in Scripture, when it comes to aggravate sinne, and to set the notorious mark upon it, that it stiles it Rebellion. 15. <hi>Num.</hi> 30.26 <hi>Num.</hi> 9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.2. <hi>Iob</hi> 24.13. <hi>Esai.</hi> 41.12. Yea Scripture sufficiently discovers it selfe, that though these Attempters are accounted by the World ennobled Worthies, or grand Assertors of Liberties, yet by Scripture they are esteemed, and named Traytors. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4. Scripture will not allow men to despise <hi>Dignities,</hi> much lesse to destroy <hi>Dignities, not to curse the King in his Bed-chamber,</hi> much lesse to assault him in the open field; No, away with this way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, wretched course, for no plausible shewes, or glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences can wash away the guilt of it; Ye may terme it an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Disposition, a Pious Resolution, but Scripture saith it is <hi>to stand in an evill thing.</hi> 8 Eccles. 3. Let such therefore take home the sting of the evill to their Consciences, and without an high degree of Humiliation from such a bad Antecedent, expect an evill Consequent, <hi>for they shall perish in the gain-saying of Corah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. Iude v, <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> that is some prodigious end, or other, that they might carry the brand of State-troublers in their browes, is designed, and decreed against them; yea, well were it, if they could make a full reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with God upon earth, and that by Racks, and Gibbets, and Scaffolds, or some immediate punnishment comming warme out of the hand of the Almighty, they could feel their last of an avenging Iudge, <hi>but they shall receive to themselves Damnation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 13 2.</note> Oh miserable spark o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Rebellion then that kindles Divine wrath; Yet a reward as certaine as just, for flames to flames, State-flames to Hell-flames. Though they receive nothing upon earth, or they receive much, yet the worst Receipt is behind, <hi>they shall receive Damnation;</hi> that they which imitate the Devill, and his Angels (as I told you before) shall goe into fire <hi>prepared for the Devill and his Angels.</hi> And thus I might leave them, that have fetch'd inventions from Hell, at the mouth of Hell, but that they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162369:8"/> may shiver the more with the dread of the torment, I will shew them more evidently out of Scripture the manifestnesse of the guilt; for if the sinne be made apparent to them, they know Vengeance lies at the door. That the violent resisting of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then is an unquestionable sinne, take these irrefragable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a sinne, because it forsakes Christs State-rule, that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty must be preserved, or casualty is to be expected; <hi>For a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divided against it self cannot stand. Matth.</hi> 12.25. Oh then if it be a sinne to overthrow a private Family, to oppresse a man and his house, a man and his heritage, with broad <hi>Phylacteries</hi> and long Prayers to devour Widows and Orphanes, then what an offence is it to consume a Nation? doubtlesse this is a <hi>Piacle</hi> scarce to be purged with sacrifice, to be guilty of the Division of a Kingdome in the first place, and the destruction of it in the second place.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 4.</note>2. Because it fights not Christs Cause with Christs weapon; for be the designe never so holy, yet the weapons of our War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not carnall; If Doctrine be to be reformed, or Dicipline changed, yet these are to be done by godly Exhortations, not bloody wounds; by judicious conference, not furious combats; for Warres are not lawfull▪ but to maintaine, or recover Titles, and those not by Subjects against their Princes, but by Princes against Vsurpers: I scarce beleeve any moderate and intelligent Divine will justify that Armes are to be taken against Papists, or Turks to propagate Faith. This is none of Christs Warre then, because his proper Engineer is not imployed. Remember that our Saviour sent out his first Disciples without a staffe. <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.10. and they were to say, <hi>Peace be to this House.</hi> vers. 12. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the blessed Apostles at their solemne Inauguration into that holy Function, had no double-edged weapons appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them; No, <hi>There appeared unto them cloven Tongues. Acts</hi> 2.3. Then <hi>Ex cijsdem nutrimur ex quibus sumus,</hi> if this were Faiths nourishment in the wombe, it may well be her succour at the brest.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Because it assaults God in his Vicegerent, for as a man strikes at the Iudge, but meaneth the King; so a man strikes at the King, but he intends God; for a man cannot separate God from the King, because He is the Lords Anointed. <hi>Who then can
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162369:8"/> lay his hand upon the Lords Anointed, and be guiltlesse? Sam.</hi> 26.9. Oh beware of sinnes that levell directly at the Almighty; for <hi>if one man sinne against another, the Iudge shall judge it, but if a man sinne against the Lord, who shall plead for him.</hi> 1 Sam. 2.25.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Because it fills a Nation full of all manner of sinnes, as</p>
            <p>First <hi>Jmpatience,</hi> for what are seditious Persons, but Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents? men fitter to resist an Ordinance, then to resist a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to enter into a skirmish, then to endure a Triall; for God must send them such a Governour as they like (and they are very curious in their liking, it is hard for God to provide a dish so delicious, that shall please all palates) or else they will ease their hearts at the swords point: if they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnot flee Gods judgement (in shunning such a Prince as they approve not) they will fl e to their weapon. But is this <hi>to obey the froward as well as the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.18. No, this is a very querulous obedience.</p>
            <p>Secondly <hi>Scandall,</hi> for the Rebell seldome goes without his complaint ready drawne, he cannot fight till he hath edged his weapons with invectives; <hi>Absalons</hi> Van-Curriours of his Army were slanders. The <hi>matters are good,</hi> (saith he) but here is no good King; No, a languishing Government, and lingring Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice; we are borne to Liberty, but oh under what a heavy bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage doe we live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with these subtill insinuations, and bitter ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies doth he make <hi>David</hi> at last to be censured here, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed there; all persons that were discontented either for want of Preferment, or for want of Liberty to set the Crowne upon what head they most aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted, disgorge upon the Prince. Thus ye see how scandall troubles the State: Subjection speakes with reverence to the Prince, but Rebellion wants her mouth-water, that hath a furred tongue against Authority. And is not this an evill disease? Yes, whats<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the imperfections of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be; yet we should be more mindfull of our owne gifts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28.</note> then his frailties, for it is a sinne to speake <hi>evill of the Ruler of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> For they seem Common-wealths-men, but they are Private-Wealths-men; they pretend suppressing of abuses, but it is supplying of wants; and getting of Priv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ledges to the Subject, but they are preheminences to themselves; they love their King, but they mean his Revenew; and they fight for him, when they discharge at him: Oh is not this delusion and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162369:9"/> learning of the State a complementall fiction, a grosse sinne? Yes, we that should speak the truth from our hearts, 15 <hi>Psal.</hi> 2. and weare sincerity as our Evangelicall girdle, 6 <hi>Ephes.</hi> 14. doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less cannot be permitted to be thus versute, and artificiall. No, these publique <hi>Larves</hi> seem to be of the old race of the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who with smooth pretences put downe one King, and set up Thirty Tyrants; or of some Iewish Progenie, who gave to their King an <hi>Ave, Hayle King of the Iewes,</hi> but withall crucified him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly <hi>Seducing,</hi> For the Rebell cannot act all by his single strength; no, he must gather a Party, therefore all his witts are employed after he hath drawn men into discontents, how he may draw them under his banners; so many as follow the King, threaren his head, therefore he must seduce, or give over his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And is it not an horrible sinne thus to separate King and People? The Scripture saith, <hi>Thou shalt not covet thy Neighbours servant,</hi> much lesse then thy Princes Subjects. Was not this the sinne of <hi>Absalom, who stole away the hearts of the People of Israel,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.6. Stole; Call it what you will, Engaging of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the common <hi>Cause,</hi> confederating them in the holy <hi>league,</hi> yet it is no other then abominable Theft, yea Felony in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est degree; for if he that breaks open the Exchequor, or robbs the Mynt, or steales away the Kings Robes, or jewels, commit an high offence, then what doth he that steales away the hearts of his people? they had as good cut off his right hand, or his left, by which he should defend himself.</p>
            <p>Fiftly <hi>Perjury,</hi> For whereas Subjects are the King <hi>ligati homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> his Liege men, they have promised to be Loyall and feyall to him, yea they are bounden to him by the greatest assurance upon earth, an Oath; these no sooner enter into Rebellion, but they cancell this assura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, and by Associations, and Vows, dejerate, unswear this Oath, as if they would sweare away their God by a contradictory invocation, or renounce an old Oath by a new Covenant; a strange kind of dispensation, an heterogeneous Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution; yet thus they abuse Gods Name, chevalrise Conscience, and that which is worst of all, insnare a Kingdome in a woefull curse; they have taken their hands from the Bible, where <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis Evangelijs,</hi> they did pronounce, all their comforts lay, and they have forfeited <hi>Gods helpe,</hi> which upon this condition they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:162369:9"/> did insure to their soules, and they have untitled themselves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the priviledges of Faith, and merits of a pretious Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which were to be conveighed unto them upon their fidelity; and indeed by this impious course they remaine but as a botch to Profession, a selfe-soules-fret, and a daily object of divine ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. Perjury is so greivous a sinne, that it is generally called by the name of Blasphemy (nay a vaine Oath is so, much more then a false Oath) and commonly Divines hold it a species of the sins against the Holy-Ghost; for can theere be almost a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sin, than to set ones mouth against Heaven, and defy ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, to seem to have sworn to a deafe, impotent, or an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary God? surely they have a weak perswasion of a God, little fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a soule, or dread of Doomesday, that make no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of an Oath; therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> frights the Subject from the least act of Disloyalty, and that <hi>because of the Oath of God.</hi> 8. Eccl. 2.</p>
            <p>Sixtly <hi>Cruelty,</hi> for when Rebellion comes, what comes, but for every one to rage upon his next neighbours, and to eat as it were the flesh of his own arme? The Rebell is another <hi>Ishmael,</hi> his hand against every man, and every mans hand against him. 16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. he hath sworn the destruction of his Country, and he careth not by what outrages he doth effect it, he knowes hee cannot work his ends by high lookes, or dry-blows, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he breatheth nothing but slaughters, and layes on none but brayning-blowes; all his delight is to dazle here, and cleave there, and to leave nothing behind him but scattered skuls, and shattered ribs; these are his pleasing spectacles, his glorious Trophees: And can there be a wilder beast upon earth than the Blood-sucker? who envyes every mans life, and fights for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, but to kill, and that every place might carry some prints of his terror, and marks of his fury; when there is no noise heard in the land but that no man spareth his Brother, <hi>and that hee snatcheth at the right-hand and is hungry, and eate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the left-hand and is not satisfied.</hi> 9. Es. 20. Or, <hi>Woe is me now, for my soule fainteth because of the Murtherers.</hi> Now if Blood-shed carry any guilt in it, what is here but a Sinne of the deepest dy? The Rebell cannot subsist, but by filling all places full of dread, and death.</p>
            <p>Seventhly <hi>Malice;</hi> for canst thou love him that stretcheth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:162369:10"/> out his hand to take thee Captive, or brandish his sword to shed thy blood? That hath no other name for thee but Malignant, and is ready to execute thee (for thy duty to God and the King) as a Delinquent? Oh will not such griefes stick and fester within, especially when thy brother hath kild that mans sonne, or that mans Nephew hath kild thy Father? Yes, as the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy</hi> said of the Lord <hi>Crequi</hi> for sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying his noble Brother <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> that there was no Attonement to be made, because the blood of <hi>Anthony</hi> was not yet dry upon <hi>Crequies</hi> sword. Blood will have a restlesse cry for revenge, insomuch that when the heate of the Wars are over, yet God knowes when the spight of the cause, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the malice of the Warres will end: Now Rebellion, that raises up s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch unkind distasts, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> causes such a setled rancor in a Nation, must it not needs be a trespasse of an high nature? Yes, <hi>they that sowe discord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and separate very friends,</hi> as Solomon saith, <hi>have ever been held deeply culpable.</hi> I say no more, <hi>but Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences may come, but woe bee to them by whom the Offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then ye see how Scriptures accurse these Wars; for the Bible hath been opened before you, and ye have heard how God upon his own Throne hath pronounced sentence against them. What now then, hath God written unto you the great things of his Law, and sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll they be unto you as a strange thing? Will ye stop your eares at the voice of the Charmer, charme he never so wisely? Ye which have seemed these many yeares to have been Bible-circled, will ye now trample the Bibles under your feet? Shall Gods will revealed be as a Trumpet that gives an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine sound? Or shall the rule of Obedience now be cried down as a false square? Shall men presume above that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and adde to this full Revelation? Would you have the purity of the Ordinances restored, <hi>and leave another Ordinance</hi> (Rom. 13.2.) <hi>in her unclean blood?</hi> Did God know Christians should have supreame Governours, and hath he provided so for obedience to their calling, that there must be such trying of it out at the sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to resolve Subjects scruples about their necessary duty? No, God which is the God of Order, and not confusion, hath setled every thing to them that are willing to receive satisfaction. They which runne to great Counsellors, or armed Souldiers, for a clearer interpretation, are as ill satisfied
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:162369:10"/> with their God, as their King. Oh then draw not a sword, lest ye fight against your received Principles, that the Word of God hath all things in it necessary for faith and manners; war not against Scripture, lest you war without booke. It will bee hard for you to kick against the pricks; this stone upon whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever it shall fall, it will grind him all to pieces; God hath set before you life and death; by these words ye must be judged at the last day. Oh therefore, I beseech you by all the reverence you beare to Scripture, by the soules check which you carry in your bosomes, that there is only to be found the infallible truth, by the infinite obligations it layes upon you for lowly, and loyall demeanor to Superiours, that ye end all these troublesome, and pernicious courses. If the Scripture command you to feare your King, turne not his feare into a fray; if that command you to honour him, turne not his honour into horror; if ye must needs be subject for Conscience sake, then either yeeld subjection, or deny a Conscience; if ye must submit for the Lords sake, then for the Lords sake expresse no more turbulencies. Oh beautifie Profession with the ancient Moderation, Patience, Fidelity, and Loyalty that belongs to Subjects; let those Primitive Professors tread out the way to you, rather than these <hi>post<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nati,</hi> new seeds-men of Sedition. Come before your Prince therefore with bended knees, rather than with stiffe hearts, with naked breasts than naked swords, with cleare protestations of duty, rather than bright harnesse; know how a King is to be encountred, how to be conquered; remember your Christian discipline, your religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous postures; let Scripture teach you your seates of Armes, let the Bible be your Military direction, let this advise you how to hold a Councell of Warre, how to fetch home a King to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For Scriptures sake then, do not divide the Kingdome any further, lest you un-Nation it; do not take up Armes for Religion, when Religion requires no such Artillery, fight not against your King, lest you fight against your God; adorne your Country with the lustre of a Christian obedience, rather than blemish it with the skars of Impatience, Scandall, Hipocrisie, Seducing, Perjury, Cruelty, Malice. Oh therefore search Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and submit to Scripture, and then ye cannot but submit to your King; ye must not encrease your bands, when Scripture bids you disband, ye must not list more Forces, when Scripture
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:162369:11"/> bids you break up the Camp; if God will have you to be quiet, resist not; if he bid you lay down your Arms, renew not a stroak; be but as obedient as Scripture counsailes you, and the insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ceases; let the Militia go where Scripture hath setled it, and the sword is restored to the right hand. Oh then if the Scripture have any power over you, the King shall not have a Subject to oppose him, no the Warres shall cease, for Scripture h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th decreed them unlawfull.</p>
            <p>Ye have now seen then how <hi>Nature, Policy</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow the action, Nature trembles at it, Policy stands agast at it, Scripture damnes it; Shall not this triple tye be able to knit a divided Nation in a firme union? yes, <hi>a threefold cord is not easily broken.</hi> Oh then consult with the tender natures in your owne bosomes, consult with Policy the home-bred States-man in your own brayns, consult with Scripture, the oracle of your own souls, and lot these three powerful Monitors prevaile with you to stint these dismall outrages. Consider when ye have harassed your Country, and massacred your brethren sufficiently; consider how many decayed men lament your discord, how many dismembred men detest your fury; consider how many ye have chased from their families, how many ye have mured up in loathsome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; consider how many broken walls, and dead bones ye have left behinde you; consider what an inlet ye have caused to sinne, what a stack ye have put to Iustice; consider what desperate Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines ye have suffered to be vented in the pulpit, and what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Schismes ye have permitted to spread in the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider what foreigne Protestants ye have left destitute of ayde, nay how ye have given occasion to your Neighbour-Professors to lay open to the edge of the sword; consider how ye have ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated discontented men of your owne Religion to trouble their naturall Princes, nay armed the <hi>Iesuites</hi> to raise tumults in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian States; consider how the Country begins to want money to satisfy your wants, and blood to spill in your quarrell; consider how many soules ye have troubled, and how many consciences distressed about these garboyles; consider what account ye will give to after-times for these proceedings, and what a heavy reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning remains for you at Gods Iudgement seat. Consider what I have said, and the Lord give you understanding; And if there be any feare of the Divine Maiesty, any reverence to supreame
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:162369:11"/> Authority, any honour to Gods revealed will, any obedience to Lawes established, any remorse for sinne, any dread of vengeance, any love to your Country that bred you, any respect to your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who though they cannot yeeld a consent to you, yet chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge an equall right with you in all the Priviledges of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if any pitty, sympathy, bowells of compassion to the groanes of the scattered multitude, or to the sorrowfull sighing of priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to the dismantled Walls, or dismembred lims, to the miseries of the tradesman, or the exigents of the husbandman, to the irrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of sin, or interuptions of Iustice, to the eclypse of the light of the Gospel, or the distempering of Order, to the disadvantage of friends, or advantage of enemies, to the wounded hearts, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted soules, to your fames, or to your posterities, to the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of your lives upon earth, or the saving of your soules in the day of the Lord Iesus, now in the midst of fears and frights, tears and curses, wants and wounds forragings &amp; plunderings, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of goodnesse, and strengthning of sinne, emptying of Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and filling of Garrisons, disturbing of Trade, and dispeopling of a Country, scorne of Tribunalls, and contempt of pulpit, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilesnesse towards your brethren, and undutifulness towards your Soveraigne; at last recollect your selves, make a faire pause, rebate your edge, pacifie your rage, consider how the Critticall day of this violent feaver is come upon us, behold how the surges rise, and the Ancho s come home, and the ship leaks, and many thousands are ready to give out their last scrike for pitty-<hi>digitis à morte remoti, quatuor aut septem.—</hi> Oh therefore kindle not more fires to consume the rest of the building, sacrifice not more mens lives to the Goddesse <hi>Fury,</hi> but if ye have any sight or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight to discerne approaching miseries, behold how the whole Kingdome is ready to turn Bancrupt, and the vitall spirits eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porating by too deep a cut in the Arteries: Oh doe not the leane Kine eate up the fatt? Doe not the servants ride on horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, and the Masters at home of high birth, perhaps Noble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction have scarce a Palfry to mount? Is not the power of the whole Kingdome generally put into the hands of spend-rhrifts? Is not the Common safety in the hands of doubtfull Keepers? Are ye not in as much feare of discontents, as of a set battell? Can a Parliament Vote, or the Absolution of a <hi>Synod</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:162369:12"/> all these hazzards? Stand ye not in slippery places? Doe not the sides of the hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e crack, and the splinters fly about, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Foundation give way, as if all would ere long fall into rubble and ashes? Oh will ye never apprehend danger, till a <hi>Non pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>târam</hi> come in; I would never have thought there would have been such an accident? Are ye so dazled with the brightnesse of your present Designe, that ye cannot, or will not see any thing but in an eclypse? There have been many hints already; warnings will not alwayes be given. If ye doe not respect your selves, why doe ye not tender those many thousands whom ye have brought into the compasse of the net with you? Would it not grieve any ingenuous Nature to thinke that He, or He should be the cause of inthralling so many willing, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>willing Wretches, which doe obey, bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>use ye pronounce it Obedience, or doe obey, because they must obey? Howsoever if they and you, and many thousands more should double and redouble your cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, that the Warres may goe on, and the sword not be laid downe so long as there be left a hilt to fight with, yet what are ye doing, but bringing misery to confusion? Our breach is great like the sea, make it a little wider, and there will be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Deluge to be seen: Destruction upon destruction is cryed, our tents will be destroyed, <hi>and our curtaines in a moment.</hi> 4 <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold one evill is come, an evill is come, yea an end is come, an end is come.</hi> 7 <hi>Ezech.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>The land begins to be empty, and void, and waste, the heart melteth, the knees knock together, sorrow is in all loynes, and all faces gather blacknesse.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Nah.</hi> 10.</note> There is a little remnant of comfort yet left, deprive us not of this, lest ye deprive us of all; No, doe with it, as with the wine found in the cluster, destroy it not for <hi>for a blessing is in it.</hi> 65. <hi>Es.</hi> 8. All the blessing that is left unto us after this great vintage of sorrows.</p>
            <p>Oh therefore make a speedy end, for feare of a speedy Ruine; Doe that now, which ye cannot doe alwayes.</p>
            <p>Now, or never therefore, Let us be beholding to you for your passionate sight of our extremities, for your compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:162369:12"/> sense of our dangers, for your wise fore-sight of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Ruth, for your grave Counsayle to prevent all mischiefs; Oh at last heare <hi>Nature,</hi> listen to <hi>Policy,</hi> and be advised by <hi>Scripture,</hi> that ye may cleerly see, seriously lay to heart, and uprightly determine how Formidable and Fatall, miserable and Execrable, unnaturall and unlawfull these Warres are.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>